<table frame="all">
  <title>Available data types</title>
  <tgroup cols="2">
  <thead>
    <row>
      <entry>Type</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
    </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <row>
      <entry>string</entry>
      <entry>Holds any arbitrary string of data.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>boolean</entry>
      <entry>
         Holds "<literal>true</literal>" or "<literal>false</literal>".
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>select</entry>
      <entry>
        Holds one of a finite number of possible values. These
        values must be specified in a field named
        <literal>Choices:</literal>. Separate the possible values
        with commas and spaces, like this:
        <literal>
          Choices: yes, no, maybe
        </literal>
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>multiselect</entry>
      <entry>
        Just like the select data type, except the user can choose any
        number of items from the list. This means that the
        <literal>Default:</literal> field and the actual value of the
        question may be a comma and space delimited list of values,
        just like the <literal>Choices:</literal> field.
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>note</entry>
      <entry>
        This template is a note that can be displayed to the user. As
        opposed to text, it is something important, that the user really
        should see. If it is not possible to display it, it might be
        saved to a log file or mailbox for them to see later.
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>text</entry>
      <entry>
        This template is a scrap of text that can be displayed to
        the user. It's intended to be used for mostly cosmetic
        reasons, touching up around other questions that are asked
        at the same time. Unlike a note, it isn't treated as
        something the user should definitely see. Less complex frontends
        may refuse to ever display this type of element.
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>password</entry>
      <entry>
        Holds a password. Use with caution. Be aware that the password
        the user enters will be written to a database. You
        should consider clearing that value out of the database as soon
        as is possible.
      </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>title</entry>
      <entry>
        Holds a (short) string that can be displayed using the SETTITLE
        command. Only the value of the short description will be used.
      </entry>
    </row>
  </tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

